[English subtitles are available]
[본 영상은 한글자막을 제공합니다]
[Road Home]
[귀로 : 너에게 돌아가는 길]
[Episode 6]
[제6화]
It feels good.
느낌 나쁘지 않은데?
I can switch with you if you want.
마음에 들면 나랑 차 바꿔 타
No need.
됐어
You're already dying.
친구가 이렇게 힘들어하고 있는데
How can I profit from your misfortunes?
친구 걸 탐내서 되겠어?
Who's dying?
누가 힘들어한다고 그래
Where are you going?
어디 가니?
Should I leave the door unlocked for you tonight?
저녁에 문 열어둘까?
Look how anxious he is.
저 녀석 서두르는 것 좀 보게
Hello?
여보세요
I saw a car parked
카센터 밖에
outside the repair factory.
차 한 대가 서 있는데
It looks familiar.
내가 아는 차인 것 같아
Tell me the car plate number.
자동차 번호를 알려 주면 알아볼게
Beijing Z52968.
경Z52968
Isn't this Meng Xiaoshan's car?
그거 멍샤오산 차잖아
Was it stolen?
도난당했나?
Or she just parked it randomly?
아니면 아무 데나 주차한 건가?
Let me call her.
내가 전화해 볼게
Give me Meng Xiaoshan's phone number.
멍샤오산 전화번호 알려줘
I'll call her.
내가 전화할게
Okay.
그래
Gui Xiao, do you still care about him?
구이샤오, 너 아직도 루천 생각해?
I mean it.
진심이야?
Let say
자오민산이
without Zhao Minshan,
없다고 치면
what would you do?
넌 어떻게 할 건데?
I don't want to talk about him.
그 사람 얘기하기 싫어
Stubborn.
마음대로 해
Did you renovate this place?
여기 새로 단장했어?
Yes.
응
Owning a restaurant needs to renovate frequently.
식당은 늘 새롭게 꾸며줘야 해
Otherwise, if it's too run-down,
그렇지 않으면 너무 오래돼 보여서
it's not suitable for a banquet
잔치라든지
or a wedding dinner.
결혼에 어울리지 않아
What do you want to eat?
뭐 먹고 싶어?
Tell me.
언니한테 말해 봐
Lamb's spine.
양 등뼈탕
Fine.
그래
It's just that you will have a bad smell after eating.
냄새 가득 배도록 먹고
I'll take a shower at your place.
집에 가서 씻어
Sure.
좋은 생각이네
Liu.
샤오류
Prepare the lamb spine with high-quality ingredients.
양 등뼈 삶아서 제대로 한 상 차려줘요
Extreme spicy.
아주 매운 맛으로요
Okay.
네
Let's go.
가자
Do you want to eat or play?
먹고 싶은 거야 아니면 놀고 싶은 거야?
If you want to play,
가지고 놀고 싶은 거면
I'll turn off the fire for you.
불을 꺼줄 테니
Take your time.
천천히 섞어
I feel like I'm possessed.
나 귀신에 홀린 것 같아
In Qining,
치닝에서
my friend's car was stolen.
친구 차를 도난당해서
I asked him for help.
루천한테 도움을 청했었어
Later, those thieves
그러고 나서 그 차 도둑들이
came to take revenge.
또 보복하러 왔었는데
He taught them a lesson.
루천이 제대로 혼내줬고
So we got in touch.
그렇게 연락이 닿았어
Did you make up?
화해한 거야?
No.
아니
He asked me to deal with
루천이 나더러 한 아이의 전학을
the transfer procedure for a kid.
도와달라고 했어
You know Lu Chen.
루천은 부러질지언정
He's always unbowed.
굽히지 않는 사람인 거 너도 알잖아
He asked me for help.
루천이 나한테 도움을 청하는 게
I thought he gave in
나한테 굽히는 거로 생각했어
and wanted to give us
우리가 다시 시작할 수 있는
a chance to start over.
기회라고 생각했지
I found out recently
나도 최근에 알았는데
he's getting married.
루천 곧 결혼한다더라
Liu.
이따가
Serve a bottle of white liquor later.
백주 한 병 가져다줘요
Wuliangye.
우량예로요
Okay, boss.
네, 사장님
Where is my husband?
우리 남편은요?
He's still in the gathering.
아직 식사하고 계세요
Ask him to come over
이따가 식사 마치면
after dinner.
여기로 오라고 좀 전해줘요
Okay.
네
You're here.
왔어?
The car is parked by the river.
차를 운하 근처에 세워뒀어
After dinner,
이따가 밥 다 먹고
help me drive it back.
나 대신 차 좀 가져와 줘
Why is it stopped by the river?
차를 왜 거기에 세워뒀어?
Gui Xiao is not feeling well.
구이샤오 몸이 안 좋아서
I helped her drive back.
내가 대신 얘 차를 운전해서 왔어
What happened?
무슨 일이야?
Was your sister
당신 동생을
bullied by others?
누가 괴롭혔어?
Lu Chen.
루천
Lu Chen?
루천?
They had a deep affection, didn't they?
마음이 깊었잖아
I just took her back
방금 얘를 운하에서
by the river.
데리고 오면서
I've been persuading her for a long time.
한참 동안 설득했어
I thought
나는 얘가
she was upset
갑자기 첫사랑을 만났는데
because she suddenly found out
자기 동창이랑 결혼한다는 소식을 듣고
her first love was getting married
잠시 마음이
with our old classmate.
뒤숭숭한 건 줄 알았더니
I didn't expect that
루천을 치닝에서
they had met each other in Qining.
이미 만났었대
It's really complicated.
생각보다 더 복잡해서
I can't make up my mind now.
나도 어떻게 말해야 할지 모르겠어
What mind?
어떻게 말해야 할지 모르긴
Just say what you should.
할 말은 해야지
Gui Xiao.
구이샤오도
You are almost 30 years old.
이미 서른이잖아
In ancient times,
과거의 일은
you're considered to have been through half of your life.
이미 지나간 지 오래야
She's an adult.
다 큰 어른을
Yet you still treat her like a child.
아직도 어린애 취급할 거야?
Fine.
그래
I won't be a parent anymore.
나도 보호자 노릇 하지 않을게
Gui Xiao.
구이샤오
I didn't tell you just now
방금 너한테 말하지 않은 건
because I didn't want you to
네가 이 일에 관여하는 걸
get involved in this.
원하지 않아서야
A few days ago,
며칠 전에
Haidong borrowed hundreds of thousands from me.
하이둥이 나한테 몇십만 위안을 빌렸어
Do you know who it is for?
누구 때문인지 알아?
It's for Lu Chen.
루천이야
About two years ago,
2년 정도 됐을 거야
the repair factory of Lu Chen's father
루천 아버지의
was not doing well.
카센터 장사가 잘 안됐는데
So he borrowed some money
자오민산 집에서
from Zhao Minshan's family
돈을 빌렸고
to lubricate the relationships
사이가 돈독해졌어
with the nearby car retail shops
근처의 자동차 판매점과
and insurance companies
보험 회사와 협력해서
and expanded the repair factory.
작업장을 증축한 후에야
Only with that, the business was rejuvenated.
형편이 다시 좋아졌어
At that time, Zhao Minshan's family
그때 자오민산의 집에서
wanted to become a shareholder and share the bonus.
주식으로 배당금을 받겠다고 했는데
Lu Chen's father disagreed.
루천네 아버지가 거절했어
Then, Zhao Minshan's family took the IOU
자오민산의 집에서 차용증을 내밀며
and asked him to pay.
원금과 이자를
Pay them both the principal and interest.
합쳐 갚으라고 했지
This old man
그 영감은
did nothing good in his life.
평생 좋은 일을 한 적이 없어
Since he has borrowed the money,
돈을 빌렸으면
it's reasonable to pay back the money.
갚는 게 당연하고
But it should not and it's illegal
주식으로 전환하는 것도
to accept them as shareholders.
불법이 아니잖아
Whether it's borrowing money or becoming a shareholder,
돈을 빌렸든 주식을 샀든 간에
it turns out to be a stalemate between them.
어쨌든 사이가 틀어져서
It took a long time.
한참을 질질 끌었어
before
얼마 전에
Zhao Minshan's parents
자오민산의 부모가
came up with an idea.
두 집안이 혼인을 맺어서 해결하자는
They suggested two families could be in-laws.
방법을 생각해 낸 거야
As long as Lu Yanchen's father
루천의 아버지가
agreed,
동의하기만 하면
he didn't have to pay back the money.
그 돈을 갚을 필요가 없게 되고
He could also spare the betrothal gift.
예물은 성의만 보이기로 했지
Zhao Minshan agreed immediately
자오민산은 루천이라는 말을 듣고
after she heard the name of Lu Chen.
바로 동의했어
That's how the marriage is formed.
그래서 이 혼사가 생긴 거야
Did Lu Chen agree too?
그러면 루천도 동의했어?
He didn't know it at all.
루천은 전혀 몰랐지
He had been kept in the dark.
루천은 여태껏 아무것도 몰랐어
His dad is indeed a dressed-up beast.
걔네 아버지는 사람도 아니야
Not only didn't he repay the loan, but he also didn't pay the bonus.
돈도 안 갚고 수익 분배도 안 하고
He just mortgaged his own son
자기 아들을 물건처럼 이용해
to the lenders.
남의 빚을 갚으려고 하잖아
After Lu Chen had known about this,
루천이 이 일을 알고
he borrowed money
돌아와서 가장 먼저 한 일이
from others immediately
돈을 빌려 빚을 갚은 거야
and asked a favour
여러 중개인도 찾아가서
from many people to persuade the other
비위 맞추고 좋게 말하며
to cancel the marriage.
파혼하려고 했어
Honey, you continue.
여보, 당신이 말 좀 해
I'm thirsty.
나 목말라
Lu Chen asked me to be the peacemaker.
루천이 나를 중재인으로 삼았어
In my early years,
내가 예전에
I had some intercourse
자오민산의 가족과
with Zhao Minshan's family.
친분이 두터워서
We did a lot of business together.
같이 사업을 했었거든
So I avoided Lu Chen's family
내가 루천의 가족 모르게
and talked to
자오민산의 가족과 만나
Zhao Minshan's family.
이야기를 해봤는데
They agreed.
그분들은 동의했어
With two conditions.
두 가지 조건이 있는데
First,
첫 번째는
pay the one million yuan back.
백만 위안을 갚는 것이고
Second, Lu Chen has to find an excuse
두 번째는 루천에게
so that the Zhao family
자오민산의 가족이 이 거래를
will not be embarrassed.
순조롭게 끝낼 이유를 찾으라는 거였어
Lu Chen
루천은 한마디의 흥정도
didn't bargain at all.
하지 않았지
He said
그리고
he didn't want the betrothal gift back
예물은 필요 없다면서
but he would pay another 100,000 yuan to the Zhao family.
그 집에 10만 위안을 더 주겠다고 했어
Lu Chen, Zhao Minshan's parents
이건 루천과 나
and I
그리고 자오민산의 부모가
discussed this matter together.
함께 나눈 얘기야
I didn't involve Lu Chen's family
이 일을 루천의 가족과
and Zhao Minshan.
자오민산에게 알리지 않았어
Lu Chen and I also
나도 루천과
had a close relationship before.
예전에 사이가 좋았잖아
But this time,
하지만 이번에는
I'll be by your side.
난 반드시 네 편에 설 거야
I've asked Haidong indirectly.
하이둥한테 넌지시 물어보니
If he clears the loan,
이번에 다 갚고 나면
his savings
전에 번 돈은
will be all gone.
바닥이 날 것이고
Moreover, 40,000 of the external debt is left.
아직 빚이 40만 위안이나 남았대
Gui Xiao.
구이샤오
This time, the initiative
이번에는 네가
is in your hands.
주도권을 쥐고 있으니
Don't act impulsively.
서두르지 말고
You have to think twice.
잘 생각해야 해
Look at you.
이 사람 보게
What are you doing?
무슨 소리를 하는 거야?
Who are you talking about?
누구한테 하는 소리야?
Forget it. Fine.
됐어, 그래
I won't blame you.
당신한테 말 안 해
Lu Chen is a nice person.
루천은 좋은 사람이야
All these years,
여러 해 동안
among these kids,
많은 아이를 봐왔지만
I only favour him.
가장 마음에 드는 건 루천이야
How high a person will reach? It depends on opportunities.
사람이 얼마나 높이 올라갈 수 있는지는 기회를 보고
How far he will go? It depends on his moral quality.
얼마나 멀리 갈 수 있는지는 인품을 봐야 해
Don't throw Gui Xiao
구이샤오를
under the bus, okay?
고난 속으로 밀어 넣지 마
I don't even want to
그 집안의 막장 스토리는
talk about the mess of his family.
말하고 싶지도 않아
Be fair.
공평하게 말해서
Gui Xiao is perfect.
구이샤오는 없는 게 없고
Every jack has its jill.
짚신도 제짝이 있는 법인데
Who does Lu Chen think he is?
루천이 뭐라도 돼?
He devoted himself
정의를 위해 목숨을 걸었잖아
and spent ten years
가장 좋은 시절의 10년을 바쳐
protecting the country.
나라를 지켰는데
Who do you think he is?
뭐라도 되냐니?
Fine, I'll stop.
됐어, 그만할게
But don't just compliment him.
당신도 너무 좋은 말만 하지 마
Let's be fair.
우리 다 공평하게 해
If I don't say something,
내가 루천을 대신해서 말하지 않으면
it'll be really unfair to him.
그게 불공평한 거지
Fine. By the way,
그래, 그나저나
marriage is a big deal.
결혼이라는 큰일은
It's easy for girls to suffer losses.
여자가 불리해지기 쉬운 일이잖아
You should have deep consideration.
더 생각해 봐
That's all I said.
나는 이 정도만 얘기하고
I won't get involved.
더 참견하지 않을게
Gui Xiao.
구이샤오
Never mind.
난 괜찮아
I just
그냥
suddenly thought of
대학 다닐 때
when I was in college,
만두 두 개로 하루를 보내던 날이
I only ate two buns every day.
문득 생각났어
Apart from him,
루천 말고
I haven't fallen in love with others.
다른 사람을 좋아해 본 적 없어
Not a single one.
단 한 명도
If we miss each other this time,
이번에 그 사람을 놓치면
I don't want to get married anymore.
나도 결혼 생각이 들지 않을 것 같아
I can live as usual.
살다 보면
Marriage is not a necessity.
결혼이 필수는 아니야
Isn't that
지금까지
how you've been through?
이렇게 너대로 잘 지내왔잖아
That's why I advise you
그러니까 내가 충고하는 거야
to be careful.
신중하게 생각해
Hello, who is this?
여보세요, 누구신가요?
I'm Lu Chen.
나 루천이야
Hold on.
잠시만요
I'll go somewhere quiet.
조용한 곳에 가서 받을게요
What's up?
무슨 일이야?
Gui Xiao had a fight with me just now.
구이샤오가 방금 나와 다투고
She drove away from the repair factory.
카센터에서 차를 몰고 갔어
I was worried about her
무슨 일이 생길까 봐 걱정돼서
and I wanted to find her.
구이샤오를 찾고 싶은데
I saw your car
네 차가
parked by the river.
운하 근처에 서 있는 걸 봤어
Is she at your place?
너랑 같이 있어?
Yes, she is.
나랑 같이 있어
How did you bully her?
애를 어떻게 괴롭힌 거야?
Why is she crying?
왜? 울었어?
Don't play dumb.
모르는 체하지 마
I thought...
나는...
What did you think?
너는 뭐?
You thought she didn't love you.
너를 좋아하지 않는 줄 알았어?
If she doesn't love you,
마음속에 네가 없었으면
why would she
그 멀고 먼
travel so far to Qining?
치닝에 뭐 하러 갔겠어?
Yes, Qining has a beautiful view.
그래, 치닝의 경치가 좋긴 하지
Gui Xiao went there
우리 구이샤오는
to enjoy the scenery
경치를 보러 간 김에
and visit
첫사랑의 안부를
you, her first love.
알아본 것 뿐이고 말이야
Where is she now?
구이샤오는 지금 어디 있어?
She's in my restaurant.
우리 식당에 있어
Don't come over first.
일단 오지 마
Think carefully about
확실히 생각해
whether you want to start again.
다시 시작할 건지 어떻게 할 건지 말이야
Think about your situation.
네 상황과 너희 부모님도
And your parents.
잘 생각해 봐
You are not teens anymore.
이제 어린애도 아니니
You need to think about your family.
집안 문제도 생각해 봐야지
Have a deep consideration before you come to her.
잘 생각하고 나서 찾아와
She's not going home today anyway.
아무튼 오늘 집에 안 돌아갈 거야
She's either in my restaurant
우리 식당 아니면
or at my home.
우리 집에 있을 거야
I'm hanging up.
안 알려 줘
You scared me.
깜짝이야
They love each other.
두 사람 사이에 감정이 남아 있는데
Can you not interfere
일부러 방해하지 마
in their affair?
알겠어?
I know.
알겠어
You don't know.
당신은 몰라
When they broke up,
그때 두 사람이 헤어지고
both of them had a breakdown,
산송장이나 다름없었어
just like they were dying.
세상이 두 쪽 난 줄 알았다고
I'm afraid they would repeat the same mistake.
난 전철을 밟을까 봐 걱정돼
Did you come to Beijing
베이징에 놀러 왔니?
for the winter break?
겨울 방학 보내러?
No.
아뇨
I transferred here to study
전학 와서
and stay with Uncle Lu.
옌천 삼촌이랑 같이 살 거예요
Why?
왜?
Because my dad
우리 아빠가
is Uncle Lu's comrade.
옌천 삼촌이랑 둘도 없는 형제 같은 사이거든요
But he can't leave his son
그래도 아빠가 아들이랑 떨어져서
to stay here.
살 수는 없잖니
Lu Chen.
루천
I'm calling you. Didn't you hear me?
불렀는데 안 들려?
What is it?
무슨 일이야?
That kid.
저 애가
He said he wanted to study in Beijing
베이징에 전학 와서
and stay at your house.
너랑 같이 살 거라고 하더라
Yes.
맞아
I disagree.
난 싫어
That's my own business.
이건 내 일이야
These are my cousin's clothes.
이건 내 사촌 동생 옷인데
You both wear the extra small size.
너희 둘 다 스몰 사이즈라서
It fits perfectly.
딱 맞네
I noticed you had renovated the outside.
외부를 보수했나 보네?
Yes.
응
My parents thought the house was too run-down.
부모님 생각에 집이 너무 낡고
They also thought I kept bothering them.
내가 늘 귀찮게 굴어서
So I asked my friend to make a design for
친구한테 부탁해서 집과 마당을
the house and the yard.
새로 설계했어
But it's not much different
근데 예전과
from the past.
크게 다르지 않은 것 같아
I really like the layout of your house
난 너희 집 같은
with a yard.
단독주택이 좋아
Are you jealous?
부럽지?
This is the benefit of living outside the Fifth Ring.
이게 바로 5환 외곽 지역의 장점이지
People like you,
너처럼 도심에 있는
who rent a house in the city centre,
집을 빌리는 건
can't live so freely.
별로 자유롭지 않아
Do you still keep the pool table?
이 당구대는 아직 남아 있네
Of course.
당연히 남겨뒀지
This is the first gift
이건 내가 고등학교 입학할 때
my dad sent to me
아빠가 주신 선물이야
when I got into high school.
생애 첫 큰 선물
Your dad was afraid that
너랑 하이둥이 도망갈까 봐
you hung out with Haidong.
아버지께서 걱정하셨었잖아
Yes.
맞아
My dad is really good at scheming.
우리 아빠의 계산이 정확했어
Unfortunately, he didn't expect that
안타깝게도 내가 하이둥을
I was the one who wanted to break up.
차버릴 줄은 모르셨지
I'll get some water.
물 좀 가져올게
Set up the balls.
공부터 쌓고 있어
Meng Xiaoshan.
멍샤오산
Why did you come here?
왜 이렇게 바로 왔어?
I want to see her.
구이샤오를 만나고 싶어
It depends on whether she's willing or not.
구이샤오가 원하는지 아닌지에 달렸어
Ask her for me.
네가 물어봐 줘
OK. Wait here.
그래, 기다려
Lu Chen is here.
루천 왔어
Do you want to see him?
만날래?
There are many eyes out there.
보는 눈이 많은데
After cancelling the marriage,
파혼하는 일은 소란스러우니
it must be troublesome.
아주 귀찮을 거야
If you want to talk,
둘이 얘기하고 싶으면
you can talk at my house.
우리 집에서 해
I let him in.
들어오라고 할게
What should I say?
무슨 말을 해야 하지?
We were quite unhappy just now.
아까 소란을 피워서 언짢을 텐데
It's so awkward to meet him.
만나는 건 어색해
Listen, Gui Xiao.
잘 들어, 구이샤오
I didn't tell him.
내가 알려준 게 아니라
But he was smart.
루천이 너무 똑똑해서
He saw an empty car
운하 길목에
at the intersection by the river.
빈 차가 서 있는 걸 보고
Then he asked who the car plate number was.
하이둥한테 번호판을 확인하고는
Then he knew you were here.
네가 우리 집에 있을 거로 추측한 거야
So you don't have to say anything.
그러니까 너는 아무 말도 안 해도 돼
Just listen to him.
루천이 뭐라고 하는지 봐봐
I'll get him in.
가서 들어오라고 할게
Go in.
들어가
You two have a good talk.
둘이 잘 얘기해봐
Thank you.
고마워
Lu Chen.
루천
Be gentle with her.
말 좀 부드럽게 해
I'll only help you this time.
이번 한  번만 도와줄 거야
Thank you.
고마워
If you weren't handsome,
네가 잘생기지만 않았으면
and it's not for the sake of Gui Xiao,
우리 구이샤오의 행복을 위해서
I wouldn't help you once.
절대 안 도와줬을 거다
Kitty.
나비야
Sit.
앉아
Shake hands.
악수
Kitty.
나비야
Do you still remember him?
아직 루천을 기억해?
The last time I saw you,
지난번에 만났을 때
a few months ago.
넌 몇 개월 되지도 않았었는데
You still remember
알아보다니
♫When I first saw you, my heart was lost♫
♫ 그대를 처음 본 순간 내 마음을 빼앗겼죠 ♫
Things between Zhao Minshan and me are complicated.
나와 자오민산의 일은 복잡해
But it's not what you think.
그렇지만 네가 생각하는 것과 달라
♫Thinking about the future♫
♫ 새벽과 황혼의 길목에서 ♫
I know.
알아
♫At the crossroads in the morning and evening♫
♫ 미래를 생각했어요 ♫
Looks like Qin Feng
친펑이
has confessed
할 말과
♫I've been alone for a long time♫
♫ 오랫동안 혼자 방황하고 ♫
what he should and shouldn't.
하지 말아야 할 말을 다 했나 보네
♫Through the dusty years♫
♫ 도망치듯 세월을 보내며 ♫
♫Still waiting in the same place♫
♫ 여전히 제자리에서 기다렸어요 ♫
♫Be brave and say what you feel♫
♫ 용감하게 마음을 털어놓고 ♫
Gui Xiao.
구이샤오
Spare me some time.
나에게 시간을 줘
♫I'll never let you down again♫
♫ 다시는 그대의 모든 것을 저버리지 않을게요 ♫
I'll finish it quickly,
금방될 거야
♫Close your eyes and get closer♫
♫ 눈을 감고 다가가 ♫
very quickly.
금방
♫Feel your temperature♫
♫ 그대의 온도를 느껴요 ♫
♫In your world♫
♫ 그대의 세상에서 ♫
♫I don't want to back out♫
♫ 난 물러서고 싶지 않아요 ♫
♫You're warm♫
♫ 그대의 온기에 ♫
♫I'm not alone anymore♫
♫ 더 이상 외로움을 견딜 수 없어요 ♫
♫Our reunion♫
♫ 우리의 재회는 ♫
♫But back to the beginning♫
♫ 처음의 모습으로 되돌아갔죠 ♫
Xiaonan is still in the repair factory.
샤오난이 아직 카센터에 있어
♫It's like this moment♫
♫ 이 순간은 마치 ♫
♫Youth doesn't end♫
♫ 청춘의 마지막 장이 없을 것만 같아요 ♫
Well...
그러면...
You should go back first.
일단 돌아가
♫I'm still in love with you♫
♫ 여전히 그대를 사랑해요 ♫
What if your dad goes again?
너희 아버지께서 가실라
♫My heart is pulling towards the way back home♫
♫ 그대에게 돌아가는 길로 마음이 향하네요 ♫
I'm leaving.
그럼 갈게
What did he say to you?
방금 루천이 뭐라고 했어?
He said
루천이
the problem would be solved soon.
곧 문제를 해결하겠대
That's all?
그게 끝이야?
What is his feeling for you?
그럼 루천한테 네가 어떤 의미라는 거야?
Does he want to make up?
다시 만나고 싶어?
He didn't say.
그런 얘기는...
But now,
하지만 지금은
he can't say that.
그런 얘기를 하기가 좀 그렇지
Anyway, he's going to get married.
아무리 그래도 결혼할 사람이잖아
Make it up if you break it.
망가뜨렸으면 알아서 수리해야지
Fine.
수리하면 되잖아요!
How many hours has it been?
몇 시간이 지났는데
You haven't cooled down yet.
아직도 안 됐어?
Qin Xiaonan.
친샤오난
Did Gui Xiao
구이샤오가 너한테
drug you with ecstasy?
사람 홀리는 약이라도 먹인 거야?
We've known each other for years.
너랑 내가 쌓은 정이 몇 년인데
She only accompanied you for a few days.
구이샤오랑 같이 지낸 건 며칠밖에 안 되잖아
I like her.
나는 구이샤오 이모가 좋아요
I like her!
구이샤오 이모를 좋아한다고요!
I want to cry when I see her cry.
이모가 우는 걸 보면 나도 울고 싶어요
Aunt Gui Xiao treats me well.
이모가 나한테 얼마나 잘해줬는데요
She even helped me find a school.
전학 갈 학교도 찾아줬고요
Uncle Lu,
옌천 삼촌
there's really something wrong with you.
삼촌은 정말 문제 있는 사람이에요!
Let's not talk about
내 인성에 문제가 있는지 없는지는
my personality first.
둘째치자
We can discuss it later.
이건 더 의논해 봐야겠네
But
그런데 네가
you liking my wife
내 아내를 좋아한다고 한 건
is a very serious crime.
아주 나쁜 일이야
If you do it again,
한 번만 더 그러면
I'll kick you back.
집으로 돌려보낼 줄 알아
Do you hear me?
알겠어?
Did Aunt Gui Xiao buy it for you?
구이샤오 이모가 사준 거야?
It's a gift for the Spring Festival.
네, 새해 선물이래요
You just said
방금 오후에
you went to find Aunt Gui Xiao this afternoon.
구이샤오 이모를 쫓아갔다고 한 거
Is that true?
진짜예요?
Mind your own business.
어른들 일에 참견하지 마
Where are you going?
어디 가세요?
To cook.
밥하러
You're so frugal.
제대로 아끼네
We're only two people.
두 사람인데
How much more do you want?
뭐가 더 필요해
I'm also here.
나도 있잖아
I came here hungry.
배고파서 왔어
Who asked you to come?
누가 오래?
You called me and inquire about Meng Xiaoshan.
네가 전화로 멍샤오산을 물어보는데
How could I not come?
내가 안 올 수가 있어?
That was my first love.
걔는 내 첫사랑이잖아
Whose child is this?
이 아이는 누구야?
Is it yours?
네 아이는 아니지?
My dad is Uncle Lu's
우리 아빠는 옌천 삼촌의
comrade.
둘도 없는 형제 같은 친구예요
Uncle Lu
너희 옌천 삼촌의
can only have one comrade.
둘도 없는 형제 같은 친구는
That's me.
나뿐이야
Behave yourself.
유치하기는
I'm glad to see you.
널 보니 기뻐서 그래
When are you going to report yourself to the new unit?
출근은 언제부터 해?
Tomorrow.
내일부터
Then you can't drink, right?
그럼 술 못 마시겠네
Okay.
그래
Have some food.
반찬 좀 먹어
Here.
자
Ask Uncle Liu
입구에 가서 류 삼촌한테
to bring a bowl of peanuts here.
땅콩 한 그릇 좀 달라고 해
How was the talk with Gui Xiao?
구이샤오랑은 어떻게 됐어?
Did you explain clearly to her?
제대로 설명했어?
Almost.
그런대로
What do you mean by almost?
그런대로라니?
Let's settle
우선 여기 일을
the matter first.
다 해결하고 보자
OK.
알겠어
Meng Xiaoshan's 400,000 yuan
샤오산에게 빌린 40만 위안은
has been transferred to my account.
내 카드로 결제했어
I bought you an investment product.
너 주려고 재테크를 했는데
When you
네 협상이
have made an agreement with them,
잘 되길 기다렸다가
I'll transfer the money to you.
너한테 줄게
What is an investment product?
재테크가 뭔데?
If you deposit the money,
재테크는 네가 저축을 하면
you will gain interest.
이자가 생기는 거지
Haven't you bought it before?
사본 적 없어?
No.
없어
I always save with a fixed deposit.
난 정기 예금만 해
You are outdated.
시대에 뒤떨어지네
Do you know
이 캐리어의 브랜드를
the brand of this suitcase?
너는 알아?
It must be expensive.
아주 비싼 거지?
Yes.
비싸지
It's expensive.
엄청 비싼 거야
What do you think
너는 구이샤오를
about Gui Xiao?
도대체 어떻게 생각해?
[Lu Zheng Automobile Repair]
[루정 카센터]
There are numerous restaurants
이 근처에
around here.
식당이 꽤 많아
Don't bother the people in the factory
카센터 사람들에게
as much as you can.
되도록 폐를 끼치지 마
Eat it yourself.
혼자 가서 먹어
The one on the bed.
침대 위에 있는 녀석은
If he vomits,
토할 것 같으면
get him a basin.
대야를 가져다주고
Otherwise, leave him alone.
다른 때는 신경 쓸 필요 없어
I'm going to report to the brigade
나는 톈원시의 대대에
in Tianwen City.
신고하러 가야 하는데
It takes some time to come back and forth.
오가는 시간이 오래 걸릴 거야
I'll visit you during the holidays.
휴가 때 만나러 올 테니
Take care of yourself.
스스로 잘 챙기고 있어
Got it.
네, 알겠어요
It's not the first time
제가 경찰특공대 가족이 된 것도
for me being a SWAT's family member.
하루 이틀 일이 아닌데
You don't need to remind me.
특별히 당부하실 필요 없어요
If someone
만약에
who claims to be my dad comes,
내 아버지라고 하는 사람이 오면
try to avoid him.
최대한 피해
If you have any trouble,
귀찮은 일이 생기면
find that person
저 녀석에게 연락해
or Grandpa Qian and Grandpa Liu
아니면 카센터에 있는 첸 할아버지나
in the factory.
류 할아버지에게 찾아가
Don't look for Aunt Gui Xiao.
구이샤오 이모에겐 연락하지 마
Got it.
알겠어요
Take this.
이걸 쓰고 있어
When I get my salary this month,
이번 달에 월급을 받으면
I'll buy you a new one.
새 걸로 사줄게
No need. This is good enough.
아니에요, 이거면 충분해요
I'm leaving.
간다
Eat up.
밥 먹어
Take care.
조심히 가세요
[SWAT Detachment of Tianwen City Public Security Bureau]
[톈안시 경찰국 경찰특공대 사단]
Captain Lu.
루 대장님
Lu YanChen, from the Third Brigade
톈안시 경찰국 경찰특공대 사단
of SWAT Detachment of Tianwen City Public Security Bureau,
제3대대 루옌천
is here to report.
전입을 신고합니다
Welcome, Lu.
환영하네, 옌천
We met before.
우리 만난 적이 있네
Do you remember?
기억하나?
Last time when you went to Beijing for a report,
지난번에 자네가 베이징에서 보고할 때
I was downstairs.
나는 무대 아래에 있었네
I remember.
기억합니다
Let's go. I'll show you the base.
가지, 기지를 보여주겠네
Let's go.
가자, 가자
Smell it.
냄새 맡아
Lie down.
누워
Go. Come down.
출발, 내려와
Hurry.
빨리
Okay, sit down.
옳지, 앉아
Come on.
이리 와
OK. Go.
좋아, 달려
Okay, let's go.
그래, 가
Hurry up.
빨리, 서둘러
This is the police dog squadron.
여기는 경찰견 중대일세
By the way,
그렇지
I heard the sniffer dog you trained
치닝에 있는
in Qining
폭발물 수색견이
had done a great job.
많은 공을 세웠다고 들었네
That's right.
맞습니다
It's more famous than me.
사람보다 훨씬 유명합니다
It is a bully in Qining.
치닝의 자랑이죠
You...
자네도 참
Chief of the Brigade.
사단장님
You're here.
왔나?
Let me introduce him.
소개하지
This is Lin Nan,
이쪽은 제3대대의
the Deputy Captain of the Third Brigade.
린난 부대장이고
This is your new captain,
이쪽은 새로 부임한 대대장인
Lu Yanchen.
루옌천일세
He is an EOD hero,
내가 어렵게 찾아낸
and I spent great efforts recruiting him.
폭발물 처리팀의 영웅이지
Captain Lu.
루 대장님
I've heard a lot about you.
만나 뵙게 되어 영광입니다
Same to you.
마찬가지입니다
Alright.
그래
You two may
뛰어난 사람끼리 알아보는 건
express your admiration after work.
퇴근 후로 미뤄두게
Are the new members here?
새 대원들은 도착했나?
Yes.
도착했습니다
What a coincidence.
공교롭게도
They arrived the same day as Captain Lu.
루 대장님과 같은 날에 도착했네요
Our brigade
우리 대대에
has 12 new members.
12명의 새 대원이 왔습니다
Perfect.
잘됐군
Take Captain Lu to meet them.
루 대장과 함께 가서 만나게
Yes.
예
Let's go.
가게
There are 48 members in the Third Brigade,
우리 3대대는 총 48명으로
grouped by three squadrons.
3개의 중대가 있습니다
The First Squadron and Second Squadron
1중대와 2중대는
are now training separately at the base.
각자 팀 훈련 중이니
I'll introduce them later.
잠시 후에 따로 소개하겠습니다
The 12 new members
이번에 온 12명의 대원은
are newly assigned.
모두 새로 배치됐습니다
Normally, how many people
여기는 몇 명이
in a group?
한 조를 이루는 게 익숙합니까?
Usually, five or six people are in a group.
보통 대여섯 명이 한 팀을 이룹니다
That's how they group
1중대와 2중대는
in the First Squadron and Second Squadron.
그렇게 나눴습니다
One, two, one.
하나, 둘, 하나
Salute.
경례
Everyone,
제군들
I'm the captain of the Third Brigade,
나는 3대대의 대대장
Lu Yanchen.
루옌천이다
Where is Mr Wu?
우 대표님은?
I have no idea.
몰라
Didn't we make an appointment at this time?
이 시간에 만나기로 했잖아
The flight is at 12:00 p.m..
낮 12시 비행기야
It's still early.
아직 시간 있어
Sorry.
죄송합니다
I'm late for buying breakfast.
아침밥을 사느라 늦었습니다
Boss, you're too greedy.
대표님도 식탐이 많으시네요
No, I've eaten.
아닙니다, 저는 먹었고
This is for you.
이건 여러분을 위해 산 겁니다
Thank you.
감사해요
Let's go.
가자
You are new members.
제군들은 새로 온 대원이고
I'm the new captain.
나는 새로 온 대장이다
As the saying goes,
중국인들은 중시하는 것은
ring out the old, ring in the new.
송구영신이다
It's a fate
우리가 설날을 맞이하기 전
for us to report here
마지막 주에
in the last week
이곳에 들어오게 된 것도
before the Spring Festival.
인연이라고 할 수 있고
That means we can celebrate the Spring Festival together.
함께 설을 보낼 수 있게 되었다
It's our first meeting.
첫 만남이니
You don't have to be so serious.
너무 진지할 필요 없다
You are allowed to talk.
질문이 있다면 물어봐도 좋다
Captain Lu.
그러면 루 대장님
Will you treat us to dinner during the Spring Festival?
설에 밥 사주실 겁니까?
Sure.
좋다
Let's have dinner together on New Year's Eve.
설 이틀 전에 사도록 하지
Thank you, Captain Lu.
감사합니다, 루 대장님!
After the introduction,
소개도 마쳤고
and also being exploited by you,
자네들에게 착취도 당했으니
now let's get back to business.
본론으로 들어가겠다
Stand at ease.
열중쉬어!
Attention!
차려!
Before you came,
제군들은 이곳에 오기 전에
you were all top-grade students in the police academy.
모두 경찰학교의 우수한 생도였다
The EOD
폭발물 처리라는 전공 방향이
requires practical
요구하는 것은 실전성과
and professional skills.
전문 기술이다
In the police academy,
경찰학교에서는
you don't learn in a specialized way.
전문적인 수업이 없다
Just like what you are now.
지금의 제군들처럼 말이다
But as you reach here,
여기서
the instructor
교관이
will teach you by hand.
직접 가르쳐 줄 것이다
Those with good qualifications
자질이 뛰어난 대원은
can become junior EOD technicians
합동 훈련 3년을 마치면
after a three-year training.
폭발물 처리 보조 요원이 될 것이고
In three to five years of practice,
다시 3년에서 5년의 실전 경험을 쌓으면
they can become senior EOD technicians.
폭발물 처리 정식 요원이자
That is, an EOD expert.
폭발물 처리 전문가가 될 것이다
The biggest difference
다른 전문팀과 비교했을 때
between EOD and other professions
가장 큰 차이점은
is that we can only succeed
무조건 성공만 해야 하고
and not fail.
실패는 할 수 없다는 것이다
Not even a single mistake
그 어떠한 착오도
is allowed.
있어서는 안 된다
Although we have EOD suits,
우리에게 폭발물 처리 슈트가 있지만
it can only block
그것은 단지 1kg 이하의
the TNT explosion
TNT 폭약의 폭발을
in less than one kilogram.
막아줄 뿐이고
And it has to be three meters away.
3미터 밖에 있어야만 한다
In other words,
다시 말해서
if the dosage is a little,
소량의 폭발물을 만나면
you are lucky to have your dead body left.
운좋게 시신이라도 남길 수 있고
If it is a large dose,
대량의 폭발물을 만나면
there's nothing left.
아무것도 남지 않는다는 말이다
Are you scared?
무섭나?
It's our first meeting.
첫 만남이니
You are allowed to talk.
제군들의 말을 허락하겠다
Of course not.
전혀 무섭지 않습니다!
This is our profession.
해야 할 일을 할 뿐입니다
Yes, Captain Lu.
예, 루 대장님
This is what we do.
해야 할 일을 하는 것입니다
Alright.
좋다
I'm done with the nagging.
얘기는 여기까지
One more.
그리고 내가 개인적으로
I want to tell you personally.
제군들에게 전하는 말이다
When I joined the team,
내가 폭발물 처리팀 일선에 합류했을 때
the old captain
당시 대장님께서
gave us a motto.
우리에게 좌우명을 주셨다
Hope you can find
제군들 모두
the sentence you want to write
자신의 좌우명을 찾아
at the end of your last letters.
나중에 쓸 유서의 끝에 적고
It's very motivating.
마음을 단단히 먹길 바란다
What did Captain Lu say?
루 대장님의 좌우명은 무엇입니까?
Thousands of firecrackers and thousands of blood.
수많은 포화 속에 수많은 희생을 바쳐서라도
Every inch of land is valuable as gold.
소중한 조국의 강산은 한 치도 내어줄 수 없다
I'll take this line.
저도 그걸로 하겠습니다
Is there anything new, Captain Lu?
다른 것도 있으십니까, 루 대장님?
Yes.
맞습니다
Tell us more.
더 말씀해주십시오
There are so many of us.
저희 대원이 이렇게 많은데
We don't have enough last words.
나눌 유언이 부족합니다
It's hard to lead a team now.
여기 대원들은 통솔하기 어렵군
I even have to provide them with multiple choices for their last words.
유언마저 골라줘야 하나?
Stand at ease.
열중쉬어
Attention!
차려
Two sentences.
이 두 마디는
But same meaning.
같은 뜻으로
I hope you will never use them.
제군들이 영원히 쓰지 않길 바란다
I shall dedicate myself to the interests of the country in life and death
국가를 위해서라면
irrespective of personal weal and woe.
생사를 두려워하지 않는다
Or
또는
I'll sacrifice my life for the nation
국가의 어려움을 위해 목숨을 바치고
and regard death as a return.
죽음을 불사한다
Form the EOD groups
폭발물 처리팀 소그룹은 3인 1조로
with three members in each
이름 앞 글자에 따라 이룬다
in alphabetical order by initials.
이렇게 조를 짜서
See you in the field in three minutes.
3분 뒤에 운동장에서 보도록 하지
Yes.
예
Leader Xu.
쉬 대원
This is the list.
여기 명단이다
You are responsible for grouping quickly.
빨리 조를 짜서
Go to the field now.
운동장으로 가
Descend quickly.
급강하는
Change into the EOD suit
폭발물 처리 슈트로 갈아입고
and practice going up the stairs quickly.
빠르게 계단을 올라
And come back to me.
여기 옥상으로 돌아오는 연습이다
Sir.
질문 있습니다
Isn't there a time limit?
시간제한이 있습니까?
Not today.
오늘은 없다
I want to
중요한 건 자네들의
examine your physical fitness
전반적인 자질이지
and record them.
성적 등록은
It would be the first stroke
자네들이 오늘 훈련 기지에서
you leave at the training base today.
남길 첫 번째 기록이다
This is stricter than the usual requirements.
이건 시간제한보다 더한 요구야
The last place
가장 저조한 성적을 기록한 한 명은
will clean all the EOD suits worn today.
오늘 슈트 세탁을 담당한다
Action!
시작!
The suits are heavy.
슈트가 너무 무겁습니다
EOD suits
폭발물 처리 슈트는
are more than 35 kilograms.
35kg가 넘어
Just get used to it.
익숙해지면 될 거다
Cut it.
오려
No way.
못하겠어
My hands are trembling.
손이 떨려
In critical moments,
위급한 순간에
you will be exhausted and sweated all over.
체력이 바닥나고 온몸이 땀투성이가 됐을 때
You will even face
자네들이 맞닥뜨릴 것은
attack, shooting,
사방의 공격과
and gunfire.
끊이지 않는 포화일 것이다
But your fingers
하지만 자네들의 손가락은
must be the steadiest.
절대 어떠한 떨림도 있어서는 안 된다
This is the first time
이번이 자네들이
you wear EOD suits
슈트를 입고 빠른 속도로
and go upstairs quickly.
계단을 오르는 첫 시간이다
From now on,
앞으로
you have training
자네들은 슈트를 입고
of wearing EOD suits and overcoming obstacles,
장애물을 극복하는 훈련을 해야 한다
stairs, short walls,
계단과 낮은 벽
holes, narrow passages,
동굴과 골목
dark room, and others.
어두운 방과 같은
You have to overcome all obstacles
모든 장애물을 뛰어넘어서
and get to the bomb.
폭발물 앞에
And your hands
손을 대야 하고
still have to be steady.
안정적이어야 하지
This is your class schedule.
이건 시간표이다
The morning session is the basic training
오전에는 경찰특공대의
for the SWAT detachment,
체력 단련과
including physical and shooting.
사격 등 기본 훈련을 하고
During the afternoon, you will have EOD training.
오후에 폭발물 처리 수업을 집중적으로 한다
Although I'm your instructor,
내가 자네들의 교관이지만
I have to work on missions
평소에는 임무에 나가고
and be on duty.
당직도 서야 하고
I have my own job.
내 업무를 해야 해서
I can't be at the base at any time.
늘 기지에 있을 수 없어
Now we have
폭발물 처리에 관해서는
five EOD instructors.
지금 다섯 명의 교관이 있는데
I'm mainly responsible
나는 로봇 실전 연습과
for the combat exercises with robots
폭발물 장치 해체 작업을
and making and dismantling explosive devices.
주로 담당한다
Not only do we have to learn about dismantling,
저희는 해체만 하는 게 아니라
but we also have to learn about making?
만들기도 합니까?
All the explosives devices in the base
기지의 모든 폭약 장치는
are basically made by the former trainee
기본적으로 베테랑 대원과
and instructors.
교관이 직접 만든 것이다
If you don't know how to make it
어떻게 만들었는지
and also the principle,
원리를 이해하지 못한다면
how could you know how to dismantle it?
어떻게 해체할 수 있겠나?
Don't you go home this weekend?
주말에 집에 안 가십니까?
Bye.
간다
Captain Lu.
루 대장님
You forgot something.
놓고 가신 물건이 있어요
I just made it
방금 만든 거다
for you to dismantle.
줄 테니 해체해봐
No explosives.
폭약은 없으니
Don't worry.
안심하고 해체해
Lu Chen is back.
루천, 돌아왔구나
You came back
새해 전에 돌아온 걸 보니
to get married after New Year, didn't you?
결혼 준비를 하려고 왔나 보네
No.
아니에요
It's a normal work transfer.
여기로 전근했습니다
That's all.
이거 주세요
Chinese New Year is around the corner. That's too little.
곧 설인데 너무 적지 않니?
You will need those at your father-in-law's house.
장인어른 댁에도 가져다드려야지
Two more boxes of this.
이거 두 박스 더 주세요
Okay.
그래
Why do you buy so many
너랑 아이 하나 있으면서
with only a kid and you are here?
뭘 이렇게 많이 샀어?
I bought them for you.
누나 주려고 산 거야
Why are you wasting money?
웬 돈 낭비야?
I have food at home.
우리 집에도 먹을 거 있어
It's New Year.
설이잖아
It's reasonable
동생이 누나한테 사주는 건
for a brother to buy something for his sister.
당연한 거지
Besides,
그리고
our parents don't care about you.
부모님이 누나를 신경 안 쓰는데
As your brother,
내가 동생으로서
If I don't do anything,
이 정도 성의도 보이지 않으면
people will gossip.
시댁에서 한 소리 들을 거야
The password is your birthday.
비밀번호는 네 생일이야
It's just that I don't have much money.
얼마 안 되긴 하지만
I've only saved 20,000 after I get married.
결혼하고 나서 모은 2만 위안이야
No need.
됐어
Your brother-in-law knows about it.
너희 매형도 알아
And the money is not for you.
그리고 이 돈은 그냥 주는 게 아니야
You have to give it back to me
나중에 사정이 좋아지면
when you get better.
다시 갚아
No need.
정말 괜찮아
As long as you live a good life,
누나만 잘 지내면 돼
I can solve my own problem.
내 일은 내가 해결할 수 있어
You are my brother...
얘가...
Come and eat.
와서 밥 먹으렴
Let's eat.
밥 먹어
Mum said Zhao Minshan came over to our house
엄마가 그러는데 자오민산이 우리 집에 가서
and cried loudly.
한바탕 울어서
Dad was so angry.
아빠가 화나셨다더라
Did dad come to you?
아빠가 너 찾지 않으셨어?
I have an appointment
부모님이랑 같이
with them.
얘기하기로 했어
Why didn't you tell me?
왜 나한테 말 안 했어?
Drive back. I'll accompany you.
돌아가서 나도 같이 얘기할래
Dad treats you not better than treating me,
아빠가 나보다 누나한테
even worse.
더 못살게 굴잖아
If you go,
누나가 가면
do you still want to go home?
앞으로 다시는 집에 오고 싶지 않을 거야
But what if you go there, and Dad hit you?
너한테 또 손찌검하시면 어떡해?
He won't.
안 그러실 거야